I think we stopped at 332.
Is that correct?  Yes.   Yes
.  Yes.  Okay, I'll start here
.  So, the woman is talking to
whom?  for
$0, so it's a misunderstanding.  Yes, she's
talking about
misunderstandings.  And I heard
you've
already taken some pictures for the river document,
and I've heard
I'll see them tomorrow of each
house, and I heard that went
pretty well, and then I'll see that
tomorrow.  So she calls him arrogant.  You
think you're a master, but you're
not
.  And we've already
discussed this, and you have no
qualities whatsoever, and you have nothing that could
give you those good qualities
.  And now we come to
332. So, you're saying nothing depends on
anything else.  You say that
things don't change.
You say that they
are firm and that they
are solid.  Is the bad part of your
own mind?  Does he think that nothing will
change?  No, not
exactly.  Good answer from
someone over there.
Yes, of course you understand that
things change.  You will z.  For example, you get
hungry after you've eaten lunch
and after sitting in those long classes,
and then you get hungrier and hungrier,
and then, yes, the hunger
changes.  So you can't
say that things don't
change.  So he never said that
her ignorance hadn't changed.
And why is she accusing him of this now
?
So, my teacher in the
history class, when one person
gave all the answers, did you
choose that person to answer everything for you
?  H, listen up
.  If things don't
come from your seeds, if they don't
come from your seeds, then things would
never change, never
change.  In your mind you think that
things come from outside, into the
inside.  $100 now for the Tibetan
word.
So, I've now voted him out.
In this country, even if you
get the most votes, you still
won't become president.   It's
called tangents.  No,
the person who thinks that's how it will all turn out
is a new student of that
.  Sir Tangi.  Yes.  $100.
S means coming inwards, coming from outside
to inside, and Tong means how one
sees things.  Song, what exactly is an
aria?  Arya is someone who
has directly experienced the teachings, who
has directly seen them.  And Sortong is the
opposite.  Song is not called Arja.  They
think that's how the world will turn out.  They do
n't see that the world is turning out this way
.  And that brings me to
another
question.  What is my cash situation like
?  So, are you ready?  Because
it's very easy now.  Easy
money.  Yes, I was in Diamond Mountain.
I made more money than I would have
at my job back home.
And here's the question: are you
ready?  So, how
many times does the word "diamond" appear in the Diamond Cutter Sutra
?  Raise your hand
[music]
.  Never.  Who says that now?
Gerze, what I'm trying to
say here is,
because you were the former director for
12 years, you can
answer two more questions for the
same money.  What is
the Sanskrit word for diamond?
And the Sanskrit word is Vajra, and the
English word that
depends on it, Vajra, means the instrument of
power,
and Veggies comes from that, meaning vegetables.
[Music]
in earlier times,
my wife
agreed, they said,
vegetables make you strong.  That's what they used to
think.  So
Badra, every time you see a diamond
or hear someone talking about a diamond,
you have to ask yourself, why is
everyone talking about diamonds now?  And now in
this class, so
diamond, uh, away person means a uh,
suspicious person.
Why do they keep saying
Diamond Cutter Sutra now?  That's
news too.  A
message.  And does the diamond in the
Diamond Nad Sutra have anything
to do with the Diamond Way?
And if you're not in a
diamond class, he says no.  But
if you're in a Diamond B-Class, yes, of
course.  Do you understand
that?
Well, I don't know, that's
a bit too much money, let's say
, answer now without money.   So
now she's accusing the devil of
saying that nothing ever
changes.  Nothing ever changes.
And why does she say that?
Speak into the
microphone now for your teacher, and not just
for the teacher, but not out of
greed.
[Music]
So some students have to pay the teacher
to give an answer.   Okay
.  OK.
The question is, why does the
angel say that it is a misunderstanding?
You say that nothing
changes.  We have
lived for a long time without touching the diamond world
.  We think that nothing
changes because we see that things are
changing all the time.
Like her?
[Music]
So, if you think that things will turn out that way
and I say, well,
things don't really change, but
not really.  If the thing exists from his
perspective, then it could never
change.  If it doesn't
come from your seeds.  What exactly is
a seed?  Why do
things change?  Because your seeds are changing.
And when the seed makes a tree,
then the seed gives the energy to the
tree, and then the tree needs that
energy, and then it dies.  And if that
comes from seeds, then they can
die, then they are impermanent.  But
if they don't come from your seeds
, why should they
change?
And she accuses him as well.  You're the
type of person who, um, doesn't think things will
change.  No, I'm not saying that.
But you believe it, do
you understand?  And then he accuses her of not having any
friends
.
He accuses her of not having any
friends.
that she is a lonely person
and he also blamed her for
never coming home.  And where
is home now in the human
mind?  So, you're only there once a
year when you're at Diamond Mountain,
in that
class, and the rest of the time
you're just worried about who's
bothering you or something.
So he accused her of not having any
friends, of being lonely, of
never coming home, and so on.
And what does she say about that?  That's me, the one who
has no friends.  You have no
friends because all the friends you
think you have, uh, do
n't actually exist.
So next time you
have an argument with your husband, you can
try this; they will
probably just
be confused.  So, if things don't come from you
, then they can't
exist.  They
cannot change.  And number two,
they might not even exist.  So,
you know the two husbands in the
kitchen.
The husband who hurts you even though
you did nothing.  That's unbelievable!
I didn't do anything there
.  Irton, where are you when someone
needs you?  I do anything.  I have not
done anything.  I didn't do anything at all.
[Music]
So don't tell him.
So the woman says, my husband, he
just uh, yelled at me, even though
I didn't do anything.  But in this
system, where the pen comes from you, then
the man also comes from you; the fact that the
man said something to you comes
from you, and then you get angry.
But if you know where it comes from, then
you can change it.  But if you if but this is
something that
lasts forever and doesn't actually
exist.  And so he said to her, "
You have no friends at all."  And she
says I'm friends with everyone.   Do
n't say I have no friends,
because everyone in the world is my
friend.  I get along with everyone.
Who is speaking now?  The angel who
understands, the seed who
understands.  Everyone in the world is my
friend.  I love everyone.
And because I come from seed.  I have
true relationships that come from seeds
.  And when I enter into a relationship
,
then I am there because I have
honored and
respected other relationships.  I
respected them and I keep my
promises,
and it's very
interesting, and that's why I get along
with
everyone, and that means if we
understand that things come from seeds
, then you can
be close to everyone, because that's true and that's the
real world.  This is the only true
world.
It's not the case that only pens
come from seeds.  Everything comes from seeds.  And
if you don't understand that, then
you're living in an unreal
world.  Then you're a little bit
crazy.  And that also means that 8
billion people
are crazy.  Well, I'm not saying they
aren't enlightened.  I'm
not saying they are.
So, she's now dealing
with friendship and she's
now dealing with the
idea that people
are naturally friends.  Everyone is close to me
because they
depend on me.  They depend on me.  How does
the world depend on me now?  From
my
seeds.  The world depends on my seeds
.  So don't tell me I don't
have any friends.  Don't say that.  I have many
friends because everything depends on me.
My mind does
everything.  So, I guess this is another
$100 question.  Everyone
is watching now.
So he says you're alone and you
're a loser and you have no
friends and you're not home for 5 minutes
.  Most of the time you're somewhere else
and you don't have any friends.  That's how he accuses
her.  Yes.  And then he says, "No, no,"
he says, "I'm friends with someone."
She says I'm with a friend and
he says,
like she says, I'm friends with someone
because they come from me
.  So the pen and everything else
comes from me, and that's why they like
me
.  These are my friends.  Do you understand
that?  And that's called addiction.
But there is now an even deeper
idea.  Do you want to
go there?  So, this is
a
counter-dependency, a mutual
dependency.  So, the pen depends on
your seeds
.  Do you want it to be light or super
light
?  So, the pen depends on your
seeds, and that's why the pen is your
friend.
Or you are the friend of the pen, because
without you the pen cannot
exist.  And so he is also your friend,
the pen is also your
friend.  Samutado, therefore, is a
mutual dependency.
Okay, I'll just do it for you for
$100.  The tree depends on the seed, and
the seed depends on the tree.  And how does that all fit
together for $100?   Okay, let
me put it a little more
delicately now.  So, the seed creates
the tree, and the tree also creates
the seed, because
you can't call the seed the
origin of the tree if the tree
isn't there.
So your seeds make the, uh, make the
pen, but the pen also makes the
seed.  Your seeds make the
pen, but the pen makes the seed
a
seed.  That is the mutual
dependency.  Everyone always does it that way.
I made that, I have that, do that. I made
the pen.  I have the
ship, but the pen also makes the
seeds, because otherwise they can't
be seeds until the pen has come into being
.  This is Diamond Way.  This is
Diamond Mountain, Diamond
Way.  The seeds also come from the pen
.  And everyone else already knows
the secret.
regular DCI students.  Everything comes from
pen to seed.  Everything comes from Seed
and Diamond Mountain Diamond Way.
The pen is from
me.  So the pen comes from my
seed.
Okay, I made the pen and the
pen comes from my seeds and my
seeds are seeds because of the
pen.  So, when you
talk about dependent origination, that's
mutual dependence, and that's
not usually how it's
taught.  So, $500 even for
Word.  What is the age-old example
of this?
the pot and, so to speak, the
circle.
In the old language, this is called, uh, the
spear, uh, for example.  Back then, they did
n't have guns, so they had to
make a staff and
then attach metal to the tip, and then it
was a
spear.  And even in war, you have to take
a break if you
want to eat breakfast.
And in those terrible earlier
battles, they would say, "Okay,
now we need to take a lunch break
."  And then they all
ran back to camp and then they
cooked something and then
they and then no one who was a good
fighter ever stuck the spear into the
ground, because the tip
would rust there.  And then you
leaned the tips together like that, and then you first have to
lean two [music] pieces together.  And what is
the
example here?  The
pen depends on the seed, but the
seed also depends on the pen.  So this
is about
mutual
dependence on each other.
Your husband comes from you, but you
also come from your husband, because without the
seeds, er, from you, there would be no husband.
So, if you have problems with
another person,
then, when you think about
this
relationship, obviously it's a
problem if you think the other person is
n't from you, but it's
also a problem if you're not from the
other person
, because that means
you're also messed up, that you're
M
because the tree also creates the seed.
And so if you have a problem with
another person, then
you have a problem and that's
tough.  So, if someone tells you that
all the [ __ ] come from you, then
you have a problem, because it's a
reflection of yourself.
They then define you.
[Music]
Okay, so everyone says they want to
study Diamond Way.
So nobody says they want to
study philosophy.  Everyone wants to study Diamond Way
.  So what exactly is she
arguing about here?  What's happening here?
So you really need to
focus on this argument now.  So
the angel is arguing with the devil.
You're such a loser.  You're coming home
.  So you're always alone.
You come home once a year.  I
only see you once a year.  And
then I'm supposed to think about the fact that the
man is mine.  But you're never
here, because you're so rarely here.  You
are so lonely there.
No, you're the
one.  I am friends with everyone
because they are the tree and
I am the seed.  They make me who
I am
.  It is very deep.
So you pen people go back to DCI
and you seed people come, because the pen
makes the seed into a
seed.
Thank you very much.  If it weren't for your seeds
, I wouldn't be here at all.
I wouldn't have any
seeds, because otherwise we wouldn't have done anything
.  The
true dependency goes back and forth, it
goes both
ways.  That means she's never
alone, and she knows it. If you
understand this dependency
, then
you're deeply connected to everyone
else on this planet, and
to other planets too, but I do
n't want to blow your mind.  If
you truly understand the pen
, then you are connected to everyone
on this planet.  If you
understand the pen, then everyone in
this world is your friend, because you depend on each other
.
Uh, don't tell me I'm lonely,
because all day long I'm
connected and friends with everyone, and
you're
not.  Not him.  And who is he?
Ignorance and misunderstanding.
[Music]
And now she continues with
a truly sexy
list.  And now she says: "Ignorance, you
're all alone and a loser. I
have friends, I have so many
friends. But you're alone." And him?
Haha, why?  Who?  Who are your
friends?
And here is a list of my
friends.  So, sunrise and
moonrise, those are my friends.  Is
that
cool?  And the cardinal directions East
and West are also my friends, they depend on
me too,
and she's now showing off how
many friends she has.
and tells him he has no
friends.  I have friends at
high levels.  I have sun and
I have moon, I have east and
west, I even have day and night.
These are all my
friends,
and then there's also summer, winter,
spring and
autumn.  These are all my
friends, and the fact that the rain
is falling and that, uh, the food is
growing, and she's talking about that.   This indicates
how many friends she
has.
and Stanley
$100.  Then you can
buy another script or part of it.
Well, he's not going to answer anyway.   That
's
okay.  So, this is now, uh, the
discussion about borders.  So, my
friends, there is this boundary
between day and night, and also the
boundary between East and
West, and in the old
Sanskrit Sima.   Did
I already say that's
$50?  And what is the Tibetan word for
Zima?  Zam.
Zam.  So, you have to learn two words.
Tibetan is tame.  Ts
is the Sanskrit word for Zam Zima Zima with a
long I.
Zima and Zima means
border.  It comes into English
as the hem.
the
seam, the seam, the seam where the
pieces of fabric have been
sewn together.  And that comes
from the Sanskrit word Sima.
Sutra also comes
from the
thread.  Sima now means
boundary, the
border, and that is very, very important for
retreats.   This is
a very, very important thing for
retreats, because every time we
do a retreat, a really serious
retreat, we have to draw a line
, we have to draw a line around the retreat
.  Two borders at least.
One
is when someone
runs up the mountain and puts a
samto down,
or you can also mark an inner
circle
and that is
Zima.  Zima, say Zima with the long
I.
So, that's the
border, and that's what I told the people
in Dünnhang when I
did my three-year retreat;
I told them all about it.  That's where I
wrote the last pages of the Diamond Cutter Business Book in the car.  And
then, when we
arrived at Diamond Mountain before the tour,
I handed her the manuscript,
and then
we parked the car,
and
then it's like
a
gate, and
then I made the promise that
I would not leave this gate
.  Three years, not three
.  And then you briefly get that
doubt again, should I go now
or not?  But then I let go
and did
n't get through this tour for three years.  And
then, strange
things happen.  For example, I broke a tooth
and then I thought
I had to go to the city, I had to get
a tooth repaired.  And then
someone said to me, "Have you never
heard of SuperGlue, the
superglue?"  But I don't know
where the tooth is.  No, no, we just
put super glue in there.
You don't need a
tooth part for that, and that's why I didn't
break the room.  I haven't passed through that gate for 3 years,
three months, and three days
.  And in the angel and devil talk
here, what is Zima now?  What
is the line between the sun and the moon,
and between the pen and the seed?  and the
line between East and West.
We also had a project in Mexico,
on the other side of the
border.  We tried to
type in Tibetan there, but all the
computers had been stolen
.  But I need to
drive down there sometime.  Then I crossed the
border and
spoke to the workers there and said, "Wait a minute,"
I said to the
police officers, "can I just
say one thing, because they don't trust you at all?"
I just want to put one foot
in the United States and
one in Mexico.  Now I want to
feel what that
feels like.  And then I'm standing there,
looking down at the border, and
then I said, that feels exactly the same
.  I don't really feel
anything.  I don't actually feel any
boundary and I don't see any boundary either.
That's just garbage.  It's just
desert.  I don't
see a border, but there is a line.
On one side,
many people are
hungry, and just 2 meters away,
people have too much food and are dying from
obesity.  So, these are the ones who are
hungry, and these are the ones who die of
obesity.  Where is the
boundary here?  Is this because some
politician is drawing a line here?
Your seeds create this border.  What she's
saying here
is that boundaries are my
friends, including the boundaries between me
and other
people, uh, the boundary
between your eye and the pen, the
boundary
between... the boundaries
come
from
me, not just sun and moon, not
just east and west, and not just day and
night
.  She says you make these
lines.  Incidentally
, if everyone believed that,
a strange
language would develop.  We went to
Dönhang.  I'm telling you so we can
speak one language: English, Chinese.  One would have to change the entire
human language, because
it is all subject to
misunderstandings.  The word "
I" is a misunderstanding.
If I am a nice person, then
it's not like you are for me
and there should be no you and no
I, but rather we should
have land.  It doesn't matter where the border
is now.  I am you and you are me.
Therefore, if you understand this, then
the partner in your head can
say,
no, I am the only one who is the
friend of everyone.  The angel says
yes, you are the loser.  You are the one who
is alone, who has no friends, because
you don't understand that you cannot
exist without anyone else.
This is very, very
powerful, and that's why it has
taken us 10 years to get to this point
.  And so wisdom
says, understanding the seed and understanding the seed
means
having true friends.  And you don't even know
what true friends are.   Because true
friends are
me.   Do
n't say you have no friends
.  Yes, it's true that I
have no friends.  I am my friends and
they are me, and that's how close we are.  And
when you understand that, your
life is incredible.  Then every
day will be truly fun.
So, if you understand that you
are other people, then you can have
so much fun all day long, and it never ends.  You
can just goof around all day
.  Seriously, really.  And that's
really
fun, even if it's all philosophy
.  That's if you
want to have fun all day, every day, that's
the real
fun.  So it's not just about having fun on a
birthday, that would only be once a
day.  What is the deeper
wisdom here?
Uh, I want to
have 365 friends with different
birthdays so I can eat on every
birthday
.  Okay, so all the limits come
from you and they might
not even be
useful, and that relates directly to
retreats.
Because the word for retreat, Zima or
Zam, means boundary, and that means
staying within that boundary.  And sometimes you can
think more clearly when you're not with 100 people
[making music]
, when you have a normal life, and that
's good, and being with others
is very sweet.
But sometimes it is very, very
important to be alone in a
retreat hut.  That is very, very nice.
And then you come out, like John, for example,
I remember, I remember
very clearly, how I looked out
of the window and said,
this isn't
fun.  So I said that this doesn't exist
.  I said I have
1000 days to live here without a
toilet.  I was in the
desert and then, no, that's no
fun.
How come?  There is no one else here
I can help.
And I don't enjoy
helping anyone, and then yes, retreat is cool,
but I can't cook dinner for anyone
, I can't talk to anyone
, I can't help anyone.  So
, what's the deal with the retreat
?  And you will be doing a four-day in-depth
retreat.  Four days, right?
You will miss other people.  So, the
first day is good.  I finally got rid of the
guy who was always
talking, but on the third day, well, now
I actually miss him and then
you'll feel a little lonely
.  And in these
times, that is the point at which
one can reflect on Bodhisattva.
So if you do a deeper retreat over a
longer period of time, you will
understand how much you need other people
and
how much fun and sweet it is to have other people
help them, and honestly,
serving bad people is even better.
It is an art form.  That's
already quite
advanced.  And now, uh, she comes along and it gets
a little
darker.  Now things are getting a little
darker.  A bit
gloomy.  Okay, now for flips.  Yes, now it's turning
.  I'm still on verse
337.
She says there's a boundary
between, uh, spring, summer, autumn, and
winter, and then there's also a
boundary between living and dead. And
now it gets dark.  How?
And she says there's
another
boundary, and that's life and
death.  And then there are other
distinctions and divisions as well.  Can
you be sick or you can be really, really
suffering in
Diamond Mountain in the same week when it's
super hot?
And, for example, heat is good for toilet seats, as are
hunger, thirst, and everything
else.  So she is now moving on to
other boundaries between suffering, aging,
and death.  Now she goes to the
four Ari
truths.  She
says I also created the boundaries between
the four Area
Truths.  So, suffering,
the seed of suffering, and Nirvana,
and I have, so to speak, the Larm Rim.
I created these lines
between life and death.
And when you understand that these lines
also come from within you, then you can
change them.  But if you don't
understand that, then you can't
change it.
Okay, if you understand the Sema,
these
boundaries, then you can shift these boundaries
between life and death.
This is a tantric
class.  So, we're working together on
a special project
.  We help
people
shape the second half of their lives.  And we are
currently developing an
idea.  And I
taught something like that in
DSEU and someone
said,
so you're now teaching about the second
half of life.
No, no, I'm emptying the first half of what
comes next.
What's that supposed to mean?
So, I'm not
interested in how you get old and develop
kidney disease and then die
.  I'm
not interested.  But the
second half, after death, that
interests me.  So, how you
transition, not how you
get older, so to speak, and
how you stretch and run better,
that doesn't interest me
.  This is the first half.  The
second half is what
happens after that.  So, if you start a new project
when you're 40 years old, that
's the first half of your new
life.
And then you have to master the second half,
after death.  So do
n't think about life as
the first half and the second half
of life.  The second half of life
is the first half, and then what comes
after that?  You die and then you have a
second half.
And if you study well, if you
learn retreat well, and if you
learn the Diamond Way well, then it is incredibly
fun.  That's super
cool.  Do you already know what color the
sky in my next life will be?  That
will show its own colors.  That's better than
blue.  Imagine if you could
plan that.  Your next childhood,
your next
teenage years.  Imagine if you
could
plan this right now.  So either you can
say Geschla has gone crazy,
or he knows something.
So, I don't care
if you
want to give away the $100, okay, maybe I'm
crazy, but maybe I know something
.  It is possible.  What do we need to
say?  Either he knows something or he knows
nothing.  Maybe or
maybe.  Yes, well, I'm really looking forward to it
.
I will see you in the next world, so don't be late